Abbot, Francis Ellingwood, 1836-1903. Photograph collection (bMS 540): A Finding Aid.
Abbot, Francis Ellingwood. Photograph collection, 1848-1904.
Andover-Harvard Theological Library, Harvard Divinity School
bMS 540
Abbot, Francis Ellingwood, 1836-1903.
.35 cubic ft. (1 box)
Photographs of houses, friends, and family members of minister and founding member of the Free Religious Association Francis Ellingwood Abbot (Harvard A.B., 1859; Divinity School, 1859-1860; Ph.D., 1881; Meadville Theological School 1863).
Gift of Theodore S. Abbot.
Access
There are no restrictions on access to this collection.
Francis Ellingwood Abbot (1836-1903), son of Joseph Hale Abbot and Fanny Ellingwood Larcom, married Katharine F. Loring in 1859 and graduated from Harvard University with a bachelor of arts degree that same year. He was awarded a degree in theology from Meadville Theological Seminary in Pennsylvania in 1863, and was ordained a Unitarian minister in Dover, New Hampshire in 1864. At the Unitarian conference in Syracuse in 1866 Abbot led a minority group who challenged the wording of the Unitarian constitution and preamble, claiming that it needed to be more liberal. The outcome of this dispute was the founding of the Free Religious Association in 1867.
Alongside Abbot, the original founders of this Association were William J. Potter,; John Weiss, Dr. Cyrus A. Bartol,; Edward C. Towne, and Octavius B. Frothingham. The objectives of the Free Religious Association were to promote liberty of religious thought, increase humanitarian action and respect for reason, and to encourage a scientific study of theology. The organization attracted members from various Protestant denominations, especially from the Unitarians, as well as some non-Christian religions such as Judaism. Abbot was editor of the Index, the publication of the Free Religious Association from 1870-1880. Abbot was awarded a Ph.D. from Harvard University in 1881.
Organized into the following series:
Series I. General photographs
Series II. Pictures and notes from Francis Ellingwood Abbot photo album given to Andover-Harvard Theological Library by Theodore S. Abbot, 1983.
Series III. Photographs of 43 Larch Road, Cambridge, Mass.
Series IV. Photographs of individulas
Series V. The Abbot brothers
This collection consists of photographs of houses, friends, and family members of F.E. Abbot's. Some photographs have extensive notes on them or with them.
For related collection, please see bMS 550.
- NOTE: The number after the slash in each entry in the following list indicates the box number, and the number in parentheses is the folder number.
- Series I. General photographs
  - Beverly, MA. Dr. Torrey's house., bMS 540/1 (1)
  - Beverly, MA. The Old Manse, 1887. (with notes)., bMS 540/1 (2)
  - Dover, NH, 1895. 20 (now 38) Orchard Street. (with notes)., bMS 540/1 (3)
  - Dover, NH,1895. 12 Court Street., bMS 540/1 (4)
  - Cambridge, MA, 1897. 56 Shepard Street., bMS 540/1 (5)
  - Toledo, OH, 1895. 17 Indiana Avenue., bMS 540/1 (6)
  - Dover, NH,1904. Unitarian Church., bMS 540/1 (7)
  - Cambridge, MA. 13 Lake View Avenue., bMS 540/1 (8)
  - Cambridge, MA, 1883. 13 Lake View Avenue, Study (with Katie Abbot?)., bMS 540/1 (9)
  - Cambridge, MA, 1883. 13 Lake View Avenue, Study (F.E. Abbot)., bMS 540/1 (10)
  - Cambridge, MA, 1884. 43 Larch St. (Road), Front and North Side and two photographs with no captions (cows in field and snow scene)., bMS 540/1 (11)
  - Cambridge, MA, 1897. 43 Larch St. (Road)., bMS 540/1 (12)
  - Cambridge, MA, 1897. 43 Larch Road, The Parlor, 3 views., bMS 540/1 (13)
  - Cambridge, MA, 1897. 43 Larch Road, The Study, from the Parlor, two views., bMS 540/1 (14)
  - Cambridge, MA, 1897. 43 Larch Road, The Study, five views., bMS 540/1 (15)
  - Cambridge, MA, 1897. 43 Larch Road, The Dining Room, three views., bMS 540/1 (16)
  - Cambridge, MA, 1897. 43 Larch Road, Upper and Lower Halls., bMS 540/1 (17)
  - Cambridge, MA, 1897. 43 Larch Road, Our Chamber, six views., bMS 540/1 (18)
  - Cambridge, MA, 1897. 43 Larch Road, Miss Hall's Room, five views., bMS 540/1 (19)
  - Historic markers: Griffins Wharf and Samuel Adams' Home., bMS 540/1 (20)
  - Pico, from Horta, Fayol, 1879., bMS 540/1 (21)
  - Meadville, PA. Huidekoper and Divinity Halls., bMS 540/1 (22)
  - Thoreau House, with note on back., bMS 540/1 (23)
  - Anthusa Hall, 1873., bMS 540/1 (24)
  - Randalls: Belinda Lull Randall, n.d.; John Witt Randall, 1852 and 1885., bMS 540/1 (25)
  - George B. Emerson, with note., bMS 540/1 (26)
  - Horsh (?) and Hammer families, four photographs., bMS 540/1 (27)
  - The Potter family, nine photographs. William J. Potter, Mrs. Potter, Nannie Potter, and Alfred Potter, 1872-1894., bMS 540/1 (28)
  - The Meddaugh family, six photographs, 1875-1879. E.W. Meddaugh, Lula Meddaugh Kirschner,; Dorothy Kirschner,; S. Pauline,; Clara S., and Elijah W. Meddaugh., bMS 540/1 (29)
  - The Philosophers. members of the Pow-wow, four photographs with notes, 1854-1896. John M. Marsters,; David Loring,; Albert Bernard Harris, and Alfred Norton., bMS 540/1 (30)
  - Francis E. Abbot, 1903, two poses., bMS 540/1 (31)
  - K. F. A., 1857, with note., bMS 540/1 (32)
  - Fanny Ellingwood Abbot, 1857., bMS 540/1 (33)
  - Francis Ellingwood Abbot, 1848, with note. Two sizes of same photograph., bMS 540/1 (34)
  - Francis E. Abbot, 1863, four poses and 1865, two poses., bMS 540/1 (35)
  - Francis E. Abbot, 1859, two copies, different sizes., bMS 540/1 (36)
  - Francis E. Abbot, 1880, (two) and one with daughter?, bMS 540/1 (37)
  - Gen. Henry L. Abbot,; Francis E. Abbot,; Wm. F. Abbot, and Edwin H. Abbot, 1901., bMS 540/1 (38)
  - F.E. Abbot,; Francis V. Balch, and George L. Chaney, two poses, Cape Cod, MA, bMS 540/1 (39)
  - Katie's Beloved friend, 1901. O.B. Frothingham, 1872., bMS 540/1 (40)
- Series II. Pictures and notes from Francis Ellingwood Abbot photo album given to Andover-Harvard Theological Library by Theodore S. Abbot, 1983.
  - The Old Manse at Beverly, Mass. 1887., 1.
    Built by Rev. Abiel Abbot DD in 1805. Bought by Captain Henry Larcom in 1831 after occupying it awhile. Mother was married in the parlor at the right of front door, as shown, May 13, 1830. She inherited the house and sold it in 1869. Stanley was born on the room over the parlor, December 13, 1863.
  - The Old Nest, 20 (now 38) Orchard Street, Dover, N.H., 2.
    This was our most happy home from August 31, 1864 when I was ordained pastor of the Unitarian Society till April 1, 1868 when I found myself compelled to resign the Unitarian Christian ministry forever. While I was preaching six months to the Independent Religious Society, and until I removed with the dear family to Toledo, we boarded with Mrs. Paul on Court Street. We started for the West about July 1, 1869. Tkane June 8, 1895 by A. P. Drew.
  - Mrs. Paul's House. 12 Court St., Dover NH., 3.
    Here Katie, the two little boys and I boarded from about April 5, 1868 to about July 1, 1869. The sleeping chamber was on the upper left of the picture. The study the one on the upper right, and behind the latter was a little room occupied for three weeks by Mother on her visit to us. The house is quite unchanged. Taken by A.P. Drew, 1895.
  - Postal of Unitarian Church, Dover., 4.
    Dear Dr. Abbot, Thinking you might like to have a picture of the church where your father used to preach, I send you this little souvenir with my best wishes. I am getting on very well, improving every day. I went down to Boston on Wednesday with one of my sisters and did some shopping. I cannot understand why I have not received a picture of this year's class of nurses, which I ordered a long time ago. I will send the money as soon as I receive the picture. Very sincerely, Edith M. Morrill, Oct. 4, 04. Postal was addressed to Dr. Abbott,; McLean Hospital, Waverly, Mass.
  - Our House, 17 Indiana Ave., Toledo, Ohio from August 1871 - August 1873., 5.
    Photographed Nov. 1898. Fanny was born in the Guest Room which opened by a door on the side porch. There was no front piazza then.
  - 56 Shepherd Street, Cambridge, Mass. in 1897., 6.
    Our home from 1873 - 1876.
  - 13 Lakeview Avenue, Cambridge., 7-9.
    Later 97 Lakeview. Study at 13 Lakeview Ave. Taken July 1893.
- Series III. Photographs of 43 Larch Road, Cambridge, Mass.
  - Exterior, May 1897., 10.
  - West side and front. 1884., 11.
  - North side. 1884., 12.
  - The Parlor. 1897. 3 views., 13.
  - The Study from the Parlor. June 1897. 2 views., 14.
  - The Study. June 16, 1897., 15.
  - The Study. Her vacant chair. June 1897., 16.
  - The Study. June 1897., 17.
  - The Study. June 1897. 3 views., 18.
  - The Dining Room. June 1897., 19.
  - The Dining Room. June 1897., 20.
  - The Dining Room and Hall. June 1897., 21.
  - Lower Hall. June 1897., 22.
  - Upper Hall. June 1897., 23.
  - Our Chamber, June 1897., 24.
    Katie's desk (my present at Toledo) - her chair, and camelshair shall - her cupboard (on which she used to play solitaire) - her little shopping bag on the gas jet as she left it.
  - Our Chamber. 1897., 25.
    Katie's little table, Mother's present to her, and on it, mostly concealed, her black walnut writing desk - the ancient four poster bed, owned by Nathan Dane for forty years, and used by us from 1864 - 1893 - the previous afghan, her last gift to me on her pillow. (2 views).
  - Our Chamber. June 1897., 26.
    Katie's workbasket - the Dover parlor chair - the Beverly washstand - the beach log and piece of driftwood in the wood basket just as Katie left them - the half-burned log of Katie's last fire in the fire-place - the gilt-paper crown she wore at the Coronation of the Queen of Hearts Christmas 1876, over the large picture. (2 views).
  - Miss Hall's Room 43 Larch Road. Taken 1897., 27-28.
    This carved mahogany tester bedstead, with the bureau, dressing table and washstand made for Grandmother Larcom at her marriage, November 27, 1800, as her best chamber set stood in the spare bedfoom at Beverly, which we occupied 1863-1864. Katie had the muslin canopy and curtains made in 1881 or 1882.
  - Meadville, 29.
    Huidehoper and Divinity Halls.
  - Thoreau House, 30.
    Where in 1856-1857 I boarded three months with Mr. and Mrs. Thoreau, Sophia Thoreau and Henry D. Thoreau. My room was the upper right one (behind the trees which did not then exist).
- Series IV. Photographs of individuals
  - My father's friend George B. Emerson., 1.
    Bought of H.G. Smith November 1901. He was my own benefactor and most kind friend in younger days.
  - John W. Randall, 2.
    about 1852.
  - John Witt Randall. 1885., 3.
    Given to F.E.A. by Belinda Randall at 35 Dennis St., Mr. Pleasant, Roxbury, July 31, 1885.
  - Belinda Lull Randall, born January 17, 1816., 4.
    Given to me December 2, 1893 at 45 Dennis Street, Roxbury. (Throdore S. Abbot - 1893: Dr. Randall and his sister Belinda were very close friends of F.E. Abbot. His valuable collection of etchings and engravings have been at the Fogg Museum for many years).
  - Fritz Hammer and his wife, of Saxony., 5.
  - Page of pictures of William J. Potter and family., 6.
    (T.S.A. 1893: He graduated Harvard1854, attended Harvard Divinity 1856. Ordained 1859 in New Bedford and stayed there until 1892. A book of his LECTURES AND SERMONS - 1895 - is being given with these pictures. It contains a long biographical sketch by Francis E. Abbot).
  - Studio portraits of F.E. Abbot. October 3, 1903., 7-8.
  - Abram Walter Stevens., 10-11.
  - Miss Eliz. Peabody and Dr. Wm. T. Harris. Concord 1885., 12.
  - O.B. Frothingham1874., 13.
  - Richard P. Frothingham1874., 14.
  - F.E.A. from Sarah Warner Brooks, West Medford,December 21, 1901, 15.
    Katie's beloved friend. With loving greeting from your old friend. The Lilacs = Xmas 1901.
  - Sheet of a Meddaugh family., 16.
  - The Philosophers., 17.
    Members of the Pow-Wow held on the first Sunday of every month from October to June at the house of F.E. Abbot, Larch Street, Cambridge. James W. Marsters born February 6, 1827. Alfred Norton (Taken March 1, 1896). Albert Bernard Harris (Taken March 1, 1896).
  - David Loring., 18.
    Born March 1, 1800. Married Susanna Frost Sherman, November 25, 1824. Died December 17, 1870. Daguerreotype of 1854. Photographed 1887.
  - K.F. A. Katherine Fearing Loring., 19.
    Copied from Crawfordsville daguerreotype of 1855. Aeat 17. At the time of her engagement. (Wife of FEA).
  - FEA aeat 11. From daguerreotype of 1848 (first likeness) For Katie., 20.
    This dagerreotype was paid for from the proceeds of The Log Hut (Contributed to The Child's Friend of December 1847) which Mother wrote at my own request, and in which she alludes to me. FEA 18 December 1890.
  - Fanny Ellingwood Larcom Abbot., 21.
    Copy of photograph taken about 1857.
  - F. E. Abbot., 22.
    Class photo 1859. 2 copies.
  - Sheet of FEA taken in 1863 and 1865., 23.
    Clipping from The Literary Digest, May 6, 1933. A new Conception of Christ. (Evidently saved by someone who thought there was a resemblance to FEA).
  - FEA., 24.
    Three pictures taken in 1880. One with daughter Fanny.
  - Two pictures taken at Cape Cod with Francis V. Balch and George L. Chaney., 25.
- Series V. The Abbot brothers
  From left to right: Henry,; Francis,; William, and Edwin.
  - General Henry Larcom Abbot (1831-1927), 1.
    West Point 1854 Chief of Army Engineers.; Phi Beta Kappa 1881. Honorary Harvard LL.D. 1866. He married Susan Everett, granddaughter of Rev. Abiel Abbot, D.D. of Beverly and lived in retirement at 23 Berkeley Street, Cambridge, with his unmarried daughter May Abbot.
  - Edwin Hale Abbot (1834-1927), 2.
    Harvard 1855, AM 1858, LL.D. 1861. Lawyer and Railroad Executive. He built the large brown-stone mansion at the corner of Garden and Follen Streets, Cambridge (in 1983 it is the site of a music school) and lived there until his death.
  - Francis Ellingwood Abbot (1836-1903), 3.
    H 1859.Meadville 1863.Harvard MA 1881. Harvard Ph.D. 1881. Minister, writer and philosopher. He was an extremely devoted husband and father and died at his wife's grave on the tenth anniversary of her death.
  - William Fitzhale Abbot (1853-1922), 4.
    H-1874. Head of the Classical Department, Classical High School, Worcester, Mass. for forty years.
  - Edward Stanley Abbot (1841-1863) (not pictured), 5.
    He left Harvard in his sophomore years to attend the Military School at Norwich. He enlisted in the United States Infantry and, as a First Lieutenant, died from wounds received near Little Round Top,Gettysburg, Pa.
  - (Not pictured) Emily Frances Abbot (1839-1899)., 6.
    In 1865 she married Abiel Abbot Vaughan who was a grandson of Rev. Abiel Abbot, DD of Beverly. They lived at 21 Berkeley St. next door to her brother Henry.